玄黄端现 太极混沌如鸡蛋
ln the beginning, there was darkness...
随着轰的一声
and then, bang...
诞生了无限膨胀的时间 空间和物质
giving birth to an endless expanding existence...of time, space, and matter.
现在所见超乎我们的想象
Now, see further than we've ever imagined...
超越了客观认知极限
beyond the limits of our existence...
那地方我们称之为"宇宙"
in a place we call "The Universe."
它们是宇宙杀手
They are cosmic killers.
它们是恒星的末路 它们是恒星的终结
They're the end of stars. They're the deaths of stars.
壮观的恒星爆发…
Spectacular stellar detonations...
亮度达到了太阳的千亿倍
A hundred billion times as bright as the Sun.
瞬间照亮了整个星系
...that for an instant outshine a whole galaxy.
大爆炸以来宇宙中最大 最具活力的事件
The most massive, energetic event in the universe...since the Big Bang.
这个非同小可的宇宙灾难带来了宇宙万物
Out of this exceptional cosmic catastrophe comes creation.
然而 有一个出现在附近 地球生命将告终结
But if one struck near here, life on Earth would cease.
宇宙犯罪一幕
The universe, the cosmic crime scene...
最暴戾神秘的罪魁祸首:
for a most violent and mysterious force:
超新星
Supernovas.
--==本影片由 CMCT 团队 荣誉出品==--
更多精彩影视 请访问 http://cmct.cc
影片压制:春树  字幕来源:五羊皮  调校:御雪寒狼  招募Q号:76846146
[历史频道] 第二季 第九集 超新星
[History Channel] The UniverseⅡ 09of19 Supernovas
超新星 恒星耸人听闻无与伦比的死亡
Supernovas, the sensational and exceptional death of stars...
创造了宇宙间最大的爆炸
produce the biggest blasts in the universe.
现在 只有极少数恒星爆发了
Now, only a small minority of stars actually explode...
但是它们就是轰的一下
but those that do just go ka-blam...
把自己炸个粉身碎骨
blowing themselves to smithereens.
释放的能量超过了太阳一辈子释放的能量
Releasing more energy than the Sun does in its entire lifetime...
达10亿倍
by more than a billion.
壮观的爆炸把大量的致命射线射到宇宙中
The spectacular detonation blasts...vast amounts of lethal radiation into the universe.
如果行星系中央的恒星
lf a star at the center of a planetary system...
变成超新星爆炸的话
would go supernova and explode...
或许就会彻底消灭那个行星系里所有的生命
it would probably wipe out all forms of life...
辐射基本上会将这个行星系的所有行星上的
Radiation would basically sterilize all forms of life...in that planetary system.
所有生命统统杀死的
on any planet in the planetary system.
像刑事侦探研判宇宙犯罪的线索那样
Like homicide detectives poring over clues to a cosmic crime...
科学家用上了现代技术手段
scientists use state-of-the-art tools...
即望远镜科技手段来寻找超新星
telescopes, and technology to find supernovas...
破解它们的产生之谜
and to solve the mystery of how and why they occur.
因为爆发使之成为有趣之事
lt's an interesting thing because the explosion...
事件已经发生了
the event, has already taken place...
用望远镜来搜集后我们获得这些线索
and then we get these clues, which we gatherwith our telescopes...
试图弄明白究竟是怎么回事
and try to figure out what happened.
因为恒星调查员知道
As the stellar investigators know...
超新星具有双重星格
supernovas have a dual personality.
它们具有绝对的破坏力 同时
They have absolute power to destroy, and, at the same time...
它们又基本上在创造自我
they are fundamental to creation itself.
超新星灭亡之时 爆炸会产生大量的光
When a supernova goes off, the explosion produces a lot of light...
但是它也将轻元素变成重元素
but it also produces heavy elements out of the light ones.
这比如铁 钙或钠
So, for example, iron or calcium or sodium...
还有元素周期表上的各种元素
or any of the elements of the periodic table...
这些东西都是来自爆发的恒星
those things came from exploding stars...
它们在太阳形成前就已经消失了
that went off before the Sun was formed.
元素产生于这些巨大的恒星爆发
The elements produced in these enormous stellar explosions...
最终造出了行星 植物和人类
actually make planets, plants, and people.
你体内的钙 你呼吸的氧气
The calcium in your bones and the oxygen that you beathe...
都是恒星烹制出来并抛进太空的
were all cooked up in stars and blown out into space.
爆发恒星的冲击波
The shockwaves from exploding stars...
会压缩周围的气体云
can compress nearby clouds of gas...
触发其引力塌缩
and trigger their gravitational collapse...
结果它们开始新的一轮进程
so that they begin the renewed process offormation...
形成新的恒星 行星最后形成生命
of new stars, planets, and, ultimately, life.
鉴于间接的宇宙旁证的采集
Thanks to circumstantial cosmic evidence collected...
专家估计宇宙间的超新星的爆发
experts estimate that a mighty supernova goes off...
或许每一秒钟都会发生一次
somewhere in the universe once every single second.
所以 这是每年大概3000万次的事件
So that's something like thirty million peryear...
最近100亿年左右一直存在于宇宙中
and that's been going on for the last ten billion years or so...of the universe's existence.
让我们感觉到宇宙有多大的是
Giving us a sense of how big the universe is...
如银河系这样的典型星系
in a typical galaxy like our Milky Way...
超新星的突然爆发每百年才一到两回
a supernova suddenly occurs only once or twice a century.
不过谁都不知道下一次什么时候出现
However, nobody knows when the next one might come.
这完全是个随机事件
lt's a completely random process...
因此 我们对下一次出现的时间一无所知
so we have no idea when the next one will occur.
有可能在明天也有可能在5分钟之前
lt could be tomorrow, it could be five minutes ago...
有可能再要等上一百年
could be another hundred years.
天晓得
We don't know.
如果离我们很近的话
lf it is very close...
你就会在空中看到非常明亮的事件
you would see a very bright event in the sky.
它甚至会亮过金星等行星
lt could be even brighter than Venus or the planets...
甚至月球
or even the Moon...
甚至可能超过太阳 只要它够亮的话
or maybe even the Sun if it's bright enough.
如果超新星和你非常靠近那小命儿肯定完了
lf a supernova is too close to you, it can definitely destroy life.
闪光会破坏大气层 燃起大火
The flash disrupts the atmosphere, burns things up.
天文学家连续不断地监视天空
Astronomers are constantly policing the skies...
对银河系里至少两颗恒星保持着警惕
keeping a wary eye on at least two stars in the Milky Way...
它们有可能发生悲惨的爆发
that have the potential...
影响到地球
to catastrophically explode close to Earth.
一个威胁就在于船底座伊塔星中心
One that threatens to blow lies in the heart of the Eta Carinae Nebula...
约9000光年外
about 9,000 light-years away.
伊塔星是我们掌握的一颗超大质量恒星
Eta Carinae is one that we know about...which is a very massive star...
其质量甚至达到了太阳的百倍
maybe even a hundred times the mass of the Sun...
生命周期很短
has a very short life...
有可能其生命很快就将结束
and it could be that the end of that life...will take place sometime very soon.
另一颗在变成超新星的危险之星是参宿四
Another star in danger of going supernova is Betelgeuse...
猎户座里的恒星
a star in the Orion constellation.
这颗炙热的恒星的个头是太阳的15倍
This seething star is fifteen times the size of the Sun.
它比伊塔星更靠近地球
This one is even closer than Eta Carinae to Earth.
约在500光年外
lt's roughly 500 light-years away.
那将是一个绚丽的景象甚至在白天都能看到
lt'll be a spectacularly brilliant sight, visible even in the daytime.
毫无疑问参宿四将会爆发
There's no question Betelgeuse is going to blow up.
有可能就今晚而我们概不知晓
lt could be tonight, for all our ignorance.
有可能在今后的一万年
lt could be 10,000 years from now...
天文时间上很短的尺度
short on an astronomical time scale.
但是 有可能就今晚 如果我们对此一无所知的话
But it could be tonight if we're sufficiently ignorant about it.
因此 每晚都值得关注它是否已经爆发了
So it is worth looking at every night to see whether it's blown up.
大量的超新星爆发不仅
Not only do the massive supernova explosions...
创造与毁灭了恒星 行星和人类
create and destroy stars, planets, and people...
勇士还以宇宙射线的形式释放出强大的能量
they also unleash powerful energy in the form of cosmic rays.
这些高能带电粒子
These highly energetic charged particles...
每天都在攻击我们地球
strike our planet each and every day.
更有甚者它们具有改变进化的能力
What's more, they have the capacity to alter evolution.
我们生活在我称之为一个不安定的星系生态中
We live in what l call a disturbed galactic ecology.
那是一个异常火爆活跃的星系
lt is a very eruptive, energetic galaxy out there...
我们的星球一直遭遇到那种东西的连续攻击
and our planet is going to get pummeled by that stuff.
专家称它们会改变我们所了解的生命
Experts say they can and do change life as we know it.
我们知道基因突变
Well, we know that there are genetic mutations...
就发生在宇宙射线轰击生命体时
that take place when cosmic rays hit living things.
它干扰了DNA内部的细胞
lt disrupts the DNA inside cells.
如果超新星就在附近
And if there were a supernova nearby...
就会有大量的宇宙射线
there could be a lot more cosmic rays...
会超过我们平时成百上千甚至百万倍
like a hundred or a thousand or a million times more...than we ordinarily get.
如果你是古老的物种就有可能导致灭绝
lfyou're the old species, it might lead to your demise...
但也有可能导致新的物种的诞生
but it also might lead to new species being developed.
因此超新星可能是变化的媒介
So a supernova could be an agent of change...
难说其结果如何
and it could be for better or forworse.
了解了超新星具有创造改变生命的力量
Knowing that supernovas have the power...to create and alter life...
当务之急是人类必须解开
makes it imperative that humankind unravel the riddle...
这些宇宙定时炸弹成因之谜
of what makes these stellar time bombs tick.
你找到了什么？
What have you got here?
不错 这个是超新星载体
All right, so this is the supernova vectors.
超新星 嗯
Supernova, uh...
揭秘的关键在于详尽分析
The key to unlocking the mystery lies in detailed analysis...
超新星喷射进宇宙的东西
of what is ejected into the cosmos by a supernova.
我很高兴这个没能逃脱我们的眼睛
l'm glad this one did not escape our attention...
因为它是个赢家
'cause it was a winner.
这是颗巨大的超新星
lt's a great supernova.
大自然给了我们这个难题
Nature has given us this puzzle.
它说我不费吹灰之力搞出这些物体
lt says, "l make these objects easily"...
而我们作为理论家就必须搞明白它的性质
and we, as theorists, have to figure out how nature does it.
和所有的犯罪现场一样
As with any crime scene...
关键的线索就在现场的痕迹中
critical clues are contained in what is left behind.
和枪击一样
Like a gunshot...
死星爆炸的热气体和碎片会推进到宇宙间
hot gases and explosive debris are propelled through space...by these deadly stellar explosions.
就像枪击有一个冲击波一样
Just as these gunshots are driving a shockwave...
你可以听到冲击波产生的巨大的声响
and you could hear this strong noise from the shockwave...
实际上是压缩并加热了物质
it's actually compressing the matter and heating it up.
超新星的冲击波同样如此
A shockwave in a supernova is doing the same thing.
随着这些弹片飞速穿过空间
As these pieces of shrapnel are hurtling very fast through space...
与周围的物质发生碰撞
they collide with the material around it...
那种形式就是冲击波
and what forms is a shockwave.
神奇的恒星爆发
The fantastic stellar detonation...
将大量的超新星证据…
shoots vast amounts of ballistic supernova evidence...
被称为残留物的宇宙碎片射入宇宙
cosmic debris called remnants, into the universe.
尽管残留物产生于这个冲击波
Though the remnants are produced as this shockwave...
一路穿行于宇宙间
keeps on moving out through the universe...
但实际上产生了一个向外冲击的非常美丽的图像
it actually produces this very picturesque image...of the shock moving outward.
那颗星掀起的气体
The gases that made up that star...
以巨大的速度喷射 达到每秒一万英里
are ejected at tremendous velocities, 10,000 miles a second.
因此 它们打造了一个不断膨胀的外壳
And so they create an expanding shell...
最终会变得非常非常的大
and eventually that can become very, very large.
这些东西将持续数千年
These things go for thousands of years...
甚至数万年
or even tens of thousands of years.
所以 我们在爆发发生后数万年还能看到它
So sometimes we can see the sight of a supernova explosion...tens of thousands of years after the event has taken place.
恒星碎片在冲击波里的高速碰撞
The high-speed collision of stellar debris in the shockwave...
产生了高温以及肉眼可以看到的光
produces intense heat and light...in wavelengths invisible to the human eye.
包括电波 红外线
They include radio, infrared...
所有的X射线和伽玛射线
all the way to X-rays and gamma rays.
天文学家幸亏有了成熟的空间仪器
Fortunately for astronomers...sophisticated space-based instruments...
如哈勃太空望远镜
like Hubble...
史匹哲太空望远镜
Spitzer...
以及钱德拉X射线望远镜
and the Chandra X-ray Telescope...
帮助这些宇宙侦探来捕捉到它们
can help the cosmic detectives see them all.
基本上你可以用上的方方面面的每一件仪器
So, basically, every instrument in everyway you can...
都能给你带来所发生情况的各方面的视角
gives you a somewhat different perspective on what's going on.
然后你将它们整合在一起
So then you try to put all that together...
不失为明智之举
as an intellectual enterprise.
像指纹一样每个超新星都有其独特的式样
Like a fingerprint, each supernova has a unique pattern...
可以以几种不同的方式进行分析
and they can be analyzed in several different ways.
我们可以做的一件事就是测量超新星的亮度
One thing we can do is measure how bright the supernova is...
那就是我们所说的光变曲线
and that's what we call the light curve.
我们可以做的另一件事就是可以测量
The other thing that we can measure...
很有用的东西我们叫做光谱
that is really helpful is what we call the spectrum.
我们从望远镜里获得超新星的光
We take the light from a supernova at a telescope...
利用棱镜或光栅将其延展成小小的彩虹
spread it out into a little rainbow, using a prism or a grating...
然后测量在各个颜色或波长上有多少光
and then measure how much light there is...at each color orwavelength.
那个条纹的分析报告可以告诉我们很多有趣的事情
Analysis of that line can tell us lots of interesting things...
比如超新星的化学成分 温度
like the chemical composition of the supernova, the temperature...
压力 气体密度
the pressures and densities of the gases...
它们扩散的速度等等
how quickly they're expanding, and so on.
从光变曲线及光谱中收集的星系
lnformation gleaned from the light curve and spectrum...
揭示了超新星相互之间的差异
reveals distinctions between each supernova.
因此这很像是侦探的工作
So it is much like a detective'sjob...
你从光变曲线或光谱中得到各种线索
where you get different clues from the light curve...
努力弄明白恒星的种类
and try to figure out what kind of star it was...or from the spectrum...
引发爆炸的原因
what made it explode...
爆发产生的东西
what the products of the explosion were...
以及爆发可能造成的影响
and what the effects of that explosion might be.
随着时间的推移 我们能够愈加深入地看到
As time goes on, we can see deeper and deeper...
恒星原始的情况
into what the star originallywas...
我们实际上就得到了恒星在爆发时的成分
so we can actually get what the composition of the starwas...at the time it exploded.
通过逐个比对数百个超新星爆发的光变曲线和光谱
By comparing the light curves and spectra...from literally hundreds of supernova cases...
科学家已经能够将超新星归类成两种主要的类型
scientists have been able to classify supernovas into two main types.
典型的1A超新星释放不出氢
Type1a supernovae release no hydrogen.
其爆发的规模和亮度都是一模一样的
The explosions are uniform in size and luminosity.
II型超新星释放出大量的氢
Type ll supernova release large amounts of hydrogen.
其爆发的规模和亮度异常强烈
The explosions vary greatly in size and luminosity.
然而 为什么会存在如此不同类型的爆发恒星呢？
But why would there be such distinct types of exploding stars?
它们有可能以不同的方式自我爆发吗？
Might they be blowing themselves apart in different ways?
科学家重点放在揭示这个重大问题:
Scientists focus their efforts on uncovering the mammoth question:
究竟是什么驱使这些恒星庞然大物自我毁灭的呢？
What drives these stellar monsters to destroy themselves?
和赏金猎手搜寻歹徒一样
Like bounty hunters looking for bandits...
如今的天文学家搜遍宇宙
today's astronomers scour the cosmos...
搜寻着穷凶极恶的超新星
looking for deadly supernovas.
用他们敏锐的眼光注视天空
With their keen eyes on the sky...
他们属于一个历史悠久的恒星观察员家族
they belong to a long lineage of stellar observers.
事实上 被人类亲眼目睹的第一颗超新星
ln fact, the first supernova everwitnessed by man...
发生在中国 公元185年 2000年前
occurred in China in 185 A.D., 2,000 years ago.
中国的天文学家极为详尽的记录了
The Chinese astronomers kept very meticulous records...
他们在空中所见到的东西
about what they saw in the sky.
具体来说 当新物体出现时
Specifically, when something new appeared...
他们记录了它的亮度和位置
they recorded how bright it was, where it was...
以及持续的时间
how long it was there.
利用中国的皇家记录
Using the royal Chinese records...
今天的恒星调查员最近发现了
stellar investigators today have recently found...
这颗古代超新星的残骸
the remnant of this ancient supernova.
它被确认为RCW86
lt is identified as RCW86...
在人马座里
and is in the constellation Centaurus...
附近的两颗亮星分别叫半人马α和β
near two bright stars known as Alpha and Beta Centauri.
在中国人发现后1400年
1,400 years after the Chinese discovery...
第一个欧洲观察者目睹了一颗超新星
the first European observer witnessed a supernova.
1572年11月11日
On November11, 1572...
26岁的丹麦天文学家第谷·布拉赫散步时
26-year-old Danish astronomer Tycho Brahe was taking a walk...
在北方天空看到了一幕惊人的星象
when he witnessed a shocking stellar phenomenon...in the northern sky.
紧贴着仙女座最亮的星蚀刻出的"W"
lt was right next to the "W"...etched by the brightest stars in the constellation Cassiopeia.
即使他看到了
Even though he saw it...
即使他已是当时杰出的天文学家
and even though he was the leading astronomer of his age...
他依然不相信自己所看到的东西
he did not believe the sense of his own eyes.
第谷不同寻常的一瞥过去几年后
A few years after Tycho's remarkable sighting...
他以前的学生 约翰内斯·开普勒
his former pupil, Johannes Kepler...
实现了他对一颗新星突破性的观察
made his own groundbreaking observation of a new star.
他围绕着它一颗星一颗星地测量距离
He measured from star to star around it, the distance.
我们现在可以用来
And we can use that now...
准确地重建它爆发当时的位置
to recreate exactly the position of where it exploded.
在当代观察员仔细观察开普勒
When contemporary investigators...
1604年的残留物时
took a closer look at Kepler's 1604 remnant...
他们发现其中很奇怪的东西
they found something very strange about it.
喷射和爆发的气体中的化学成分详细分析
A detailed analysis of the chemical composition...of the ejected and expanding gases...
表明有两颗恒星以某种方式纠集在一起
indicated that there were two stars that somehow conjoined...
产生了巨大的爆发
to produce a gigantic explosion.
那么 这对伴侣是如何引发这星灾的呢？
So how did this companion cause the stellar catastrophe?
很多恒星都是双星系统
Many stars are in binary systems...
所以它们都有一个伙伴围绕着它们
so they have a partner that is orbiting around them.
我们认为结果是一颗恒星将质量转移给另一颗
And we think what happens is that one star puts mass onto the other.
专家们已经发现
Experts have since found...
那种结伴或双星的场景是所谓的1A超新星的特征
that the companion, or binary, scenario is the hallmark...of what is called a Type 1a supernova.
I型超新星 我们认为是白矮星的爆发
The Type l supernovae, we think, are the explosion of white dwarfs.
太阳这样的恒星会变成不大的致密的金块
So a star like the Sun will produce a little, dense nugget...
如地球一般大小
about the size of the Earth.
在太阳一般的恒星垂死时 会喷出其外层
When a star like the Sun dies, it ejects its outer layers...
只留下不大的 致密的 枯竭的内核
and leaves behind just a small, dense, burnt-out core...
叫做白矮星
called a white dwarf.
太阳的尸体将成为碳氧白矮星
The ashes of the Sun will be a carbon-and-oxygen white dwarf.
任其自生自灭
Left to its own devices...
最后将永远冷却
that will just last forever and cool off.
然而 恒星一旦有了伴就像罪犯有了搭档一样
But when a star has a companion, like a partner in crime...
就会导致灾难
it can lead to catastrophe.
一颗恒星将质量转移给白矮星
One star puts mass onto that white dwarf...
将质量增加到了变得不稳定的地步
pushes its mass up to the point where it becomes unstable...
其中心就会发生燃烧
and there is burning that takes place in the center.
很快
And very, very rapidly...
这颗恒星就会从乏善可陈的白矮星变成
the star goes from being a kind of boring white dwarf...
一颗极其暴戾 明亮的超新星
to being a tremendously violent and brilliant supernova.
然而 为何某些白矮星会悲惨地爆发呢？
But why do some white dwarfs catastrophically explode?
那在1930年就被搞明白了
That was figured out in 1930...
解答人是才华横溢的年轻天体物理学家
by a brilliant young astrophysicist,
苏布拉马尼扬·钱德拉塞卡
Subrahmanyan Chandrasekhar...
天文界的福尔摩斯
the Sherlock Holmes of astrophysics...
在坐船从印度到英国期间
on a boat trip from lndia to England.
在那个长途旅行中 他利用量子力学
During this long voyage, he used the newly developed fields...
和狭义相对论新开发的领域
of quantum physics and special relativity...
形成了概念
to come up with the idea...
即白矮星只能有一定限量的质量最大值
that a white dwarf can have only a certain maximum limiting mass.
你无法超越某个特定的量
You cannot go beyond a certain mass...
约比我们太阳大四成
about forty percent bigger than that of our Sun...
1.4个太阳质量
1.4 solar masses.
这个后来被称为钱德拉塞卡极限
And this came to be known as the Chandrasekhar Limit.
在那一点上失控的话
And at that point...
失控的核连锁反应随之发生
an uncontrolled, runaway chain of nuclear reactions ensues.
然而几十年里科学调查员依然心存疑惑
But for decades, scientific investigators remained puzzled...
这个爆发的连锁反应是如何运作的
by just how this explosive chain reaction worked...
以及发生时究竟是怎么个情况
and what it looked like when it did.
计算机模型一直无法重建
Computer models could never recreate...
似乎只能在大自然里发生的情况
what seemed to be happening in nature.
然而 在2006年 来自著名的芝加哥大学
But then, in 2006, astrophysicists...
闪存中心的天体物理学家
from the University of Chicago's prestigious Flash Center...
一点一点解开了密码
literally cracked the code.
芝加哥团队最早开发出超级计算机程序
The Chicago team was the first to create a supercomputer program...
能够处理海量数据
capable of processing the vast amounts of data.
它必须是可以模拟复杂的动力学
lt had to be to simulate the complicated dynamics...
涉及整个恒星的爆发
involved in the explosion of a whole star.
我们称这为极端计算
We call this extreme computing.
我们用的计算机其中一些有12.8万个处理器
The computers we use, some of them have 128,000 processors.
所以 它们其实是将12.8万台台式计算机连在一起
So they're really128,000 desktop computers all linked together.
即使那样强大
Even with all that power...
也几乎需要6万个小时的运算时间
it took almost 60,000 hours of computing time.
天文物理学家肯定模拟爆发并不是从
The astrophysicists decided not to start their simulated explosion...
恒星的中心开始的
exactly at the center of the star.
我们确认开始于稍微偏离中心
The reason that we decided to start slightly off-center...
而不是正好在其中心的理由
rather than right at the center...
在于那是非常非常不可能
is that it's just very, very improbable...
火焰会刚好或非常接近中心点燃的
that the flame will ignite exactly or even really close to the center.
那里已经没有容量了
There's just no volume there.
那里已经没有容身之地了
There's no "there" there.
根据这个不寻常的模拟
According to the remarkable simulation...
一秒钟内恒星内部形成火舌
in one second, a flame bubble forms inside the star.
所以你看到在恒星的中心
So what you see right in the center of the star...
火舌快速升起 生成 膨胀
is the bubble rising quickly, growing, expanding...
随着燃烧的发生
as the burning takes place...
突出恒星的表面
and breaking through the surface of the star.
熔化的泡沫最初测量宽约10英里
The molten bubble initially measures approximately ten miles across...
腾起恒星表面超过了1200英里
and rises more than 1,200 miles to the surface of the star.
它在恒星表面的蔓延速度为每秒3000英里
lt's spreading over the star at about 3,000 miles a second...
它与恒星表面对面的一点发生冲突
and it collides at the opposite point on the surface of the star...
产生异常猛烈的喷射
and produces extremely energeticjets...
一个向外速度达到每秒4万英里
one that's moving outward at about 40,000 miles a second...
而另一个对恒星施加压力
anotherjet that's punching in towards the star...
引发爆震波
and that ignites a detonation wave...
这个就是你看到的整个恒星的瞬间
which you've just seen race through the star.
炙热的温度用标准温标来描述
Torrid temperatures, depicted using a standard color scale...
达到了难以置信的30亿华氏度
reach an unfathomable three billion degrees Fahrenheit.
你可以看到的瞬间就是爆炸
And you can see the moment, it's just detonated...
历经那颗星还不到半秒钟
and going through the star takes less than half a second.
整个燃烧过程不足3秒钟
The whole burning phase takes less than three seconds.
专家分析显示每个1A型超新星的
Expert analysis reveals that each Type 1a supernova...
规模和亮度极其相似
is remarkably similar in size and brilliance.
爆发相当于太阳规模的质量的整体爆炸
This explosion is equivalent...to completely detonating a mass the size of the Sun.
这个突破性的计算机模拟
This groundbreaking computer simulation...
第一次演示了
illustrates for the first time...
1A型超新星是如何发生的
how the explosions could occur in a Type1a supernova.
然而II型似乎是全然不同的野兽
But Type lls seem to be a radically different animal.
通过审视恒星碎片
By examining the stellar debris...
科学家已经明白了II型超新星
scientists have reasoned that Type ll supernovas...
不是白矮星爆发的结果
are not the result of exploding white dwarfs...
而恰恰是超大垂死恒星的巨大爆发
but rather the huge blasts of massive dying stars...
其质量至少是太阳10倍
at least ten times the mass of the Sun.
然而 这些超级爆发又是如何运作的呢？
But how do these mega-explosions work?
这个宇宙难题的答案
The answer to the cosmic conundrum...
出现在20世纪中叶
would come in the middle of the 20th century.
那是超新星侦探史上首次
That's when supernova gumshoes, for the first time in history...
巡逻在银河系的路面上
pounded the intergalactic pavements...
系统地搜寻巨大的恒星爆炸
systematically seeking gigantic exploding stars.
犹如盯梢的侦探
Like detectives on a stakeout...
宇宙调查员们持续不断地密切注视着夜空
cosmic investigators constantly scan the night sky.
它们搜寻着暴露实情的亮光
They're looking for the telltale bright lights...
那可是超新星的证据
that are evidence of a supernova.
为了执行盯梢任务
To carry out their surveillance...
他们用上了散布在全球各地的一系列卓越的望远镜
they use an impressive array of high-tech telescopes...scattered across the globe.
在历史上我们用地面望远镜发现超新星
Historically, we discover supernovae with ground-based telescopes...
也就是坚持不懈地扫描天空
either scanning the sky constantly...
来寻找新的超新星爆发
to look for new supernovae explosions.
宇宙超新星搜寻始于1930年代
The cosmic supernova hunt began in the 1930s.
标新立异的天体物理学家弗里茨·兹维基首当其冲
Maverick astrophysicist Fritz Zwicky led the charge.
他是系统搜索编制目录及量化新爆发恒星的第一人
He was the first to methodically search...catalog, and quantify new and exploding stars.
他是发现爆发恒星真正的先驱之一
He was one of the real pioneers in finding exploding stars.
后来 他想理性地认识它们的属性
And then he wanted to physically understand what they are.
这个开拓性的天体物理学家
The trailblazing astrophysicist...
认为这些庞大而壮观的恒星事件
proposed that these enormous and spectacular stellar events...
是整个恒星爆发的结果
were the result of whole stars exploding.
兹维基预言某种爆发恒星
Zwicky predicted that a certain kind of exploding star...
是发生在大质量恒星的内核塌落时
can occurwhen a massive star"s core collapses...
然后 反弹创造出巨大的爆发
and then rebounds, creating a colossal explosion.
在其塌落的过程中他们认为
During the collapse, they said...
压缩的残骸应该会形成
a compact remnant should be formed...
一个中子球 即中子星
a ball of neutrons, a neutron star.
本质上普通物质是由质子 中子 电子构成的
Essentially, ordinary matter...is made out of protons and neutrons and electrons.
在铁核的塌落中
ln this collapse of an iron core...
构成铁原子的质子和电子
the protons and the electrons that make up the iron atoms...
结合产生了中子
combine to make neutrons.
中子星是密度大得惊人的天体
A neutron star is an incredibly dense object.
如果 你将一座大楼
Now, if you were to take a large building...
比如纽约的帝国大厦
like the Empire State Building in New York...
压缩到中子星的密度
and compress it to the density of a neutron star...
就会像弹子那般大小
it would be about the size of a marble.
它们具有极高的密度
They have a very high density.
事实上 一茶匙中子星的物质
And, in fact, a teaspoon of neutron star material...
在地球上将重达10亿吨
would weigh as much as one billion tons on Earth.
科学家今天认为 只有至少是太阳质量
Scientists today believe that only huge stars...
10倍的巨大恒星
at least ten times the mass of the Sun...
才有可能产生这种内核塌落式的爆发
have the potential to generate this core-collapse-type explosion.
大质量恒星通过把氢聚合成氦产生能量
The massive star generates energy by fusing hydrogen to helium.
能够将氦聚合成碳和氧
lt can fuse helium into carbon and oxygen.
一直进行下去直到产生铁
And it keeps on going all the way up to make iron.
铁是原子核约束最紧固
lron is the most tightly bound nucleus.
所以 一旦恒星是由铁构成的
So when a star is made of iron...
那确实是走到尽头了 真的是场灾难
it's really at the end of the line, and it's ready for disaster.
铁核是恒星生命的末日
The iron core forms in the last day of the star's life.
于是它变得非常庞大
And then it becomes so massive...
基本上在自己的重量下塌落
that, essentially, it collapses under its own weight...
就是重力塌落 极其快
just collapses gravitationally, very quickly.
恒星内核的塌缩用不了一秒钟
lt takes less than a second...for the core of the star to crunch down...
从地球大小到直径10到15英里大小的中子星
from something about the size of the Earth...to a neutron star, which is maybe ten or fifteen miles across.
然而 这个致密的铁核不会就这么平静地
But this dense iron core doesn't settle down peacefully...
开始中子星的新生命
into its new life as a neutron star.
但是不是马上就达到平衡的结构
But instead of reaching an equilibrium configuration right away...
中子星会自我反弹
the neutron star rebounds off of itself...
就像体操运动员在蹦床上反弹一样
just as the gymnast rebounds off of the trampoline...
再次向上跳起
and goes upward again.
这个反弹的中子星
Well, this rebounding neutron star...
与周围的物质碰撞
collides with the material surrounding it...
将自己的一定能量传给碰撞的物质
and imparts some of its energy to that colliding material...
于是引发了喷射
thus initiating an ejection.
可是 不同于体操运动员
However, unlike a gymnast...
最终重力会占上风将其拉回地球
forwhom gravity ultimately prevails, pulling him back to Earth...
在内核塌缩的场景中
in a core-collapse scenario...
有些东西会源源不断地将喷射往外推
something else continues to drive the ejection outward.
接下来的问题是
The question became...
这个将爆发推向太空的神秘力量究竟是什么呢？
what was this mysterious force driving the blast into space?
专家们计算为了让一个成功的爆炸发生
Experts calculated that in order for a successful explosion to occur...
需要其它的因素
one more ingredient was needed.
他们怀疑一种叫中微子的东西
They suspected something called neutrinos...
幽灵 具有能量的粒子
ghostly, energy-bearing particles...
预测到了 但从未发现过
that had been predicted, but never observed.
天体物理学家认为 在内核塌落期间
Astrophysicists believe that during a core collapse...
电子被挤压得非常贴近原子核里的质子
when the electrons are pushed so close to protons...in the nuclei of atoms...
一起结合成中子
that they combine to become neutrons.
在这个过程中 它们释放出这些微小的神秘的中微子
ln the process, they release these tiny, mysterious neutrino particles.
中微子是一种有趣的粒子
The neutrinos are kind of interesting particles.
它们不带任何电荷
They don't have any electric charge...
所以不会与光发生作用
so they don't interact with light.
它们的相互影响只靠物理学家所谓的弱力
They only interact by what physicists call the weak force...
弱力的命名相当恰当
and the weak force is aptly named.
这意味着这些粒子轻易穿透地球
lt means that these particles can go right through the Earth.
它们能够穿透厚厚的物质
They can go through long chunks of matter.
所以它们就像幽灵一般
So they're like ghosts.
它们穿行自如
They just go through things.
几百年来现代天文学家
For centuries, modern astronomers...
一直在研究很久以前遥远星系里的超新星的残骸
have been studying the remnants of supernovas...in faraway galaxies from the distant past.
然而 到了1987年 他们取得了突破
But in 1987, they would get a front-row seat...
目睹了一场爆发
to an explosion of theirvery own.
这是望远镜发明近四百年来
lt was the brightest supernova seen in nearly four centuries...
最亮的一次超新星爆炸
long after the development of the telescope.
所以我们可以用仪器全副武装
So we could use ourfull arsenal of equipment...
来研究这个神奇的爆炸
to study this fantastic blast.
1987年 望远镜发明以来
ln 1987, the most fantastic stellar event near our galaxy...
最神奇的星际事件就发生在我们银河系旁
since the invention of the telescope occurred.
最先看发现它的
The first to witness it...
是年轻的智利天文学家奥斯卡·杜亚尔德
was young Chilean astronomer Oscar Duhalde.
他以及天文学的好运
His and astronomy's good fortune...
出现在1987年2月23日夜晚
came on the night of February 23, 1987.
拉斯坎帕纳斯天文台的望远镜操作员
A telescope operator at the Las Campanas Observatories...
奥斯卡·杜亚尔德 冲好咖啡
Oscar Duhalde, put water on for coffee...
走到外面抬头望了一下夜空
and went outside to take a look at the sky.
当时奥斯卡走到那里
And when Oscarwent out there...
看了一下大麦哲伦星云
he looked at the Large Magellanic Cloud...
他对它了如指掌
which he knows very well...
他注意到那里多出了一颗星
and he noticed that there was an extra star.
所以他发现这颗超新星爆发
So he discovered this supernova explosion...
基本上是跑出了天文台
by basically running outside the telescope building...
用肉眼看到的
and saw it with his own eyes.
在恒星爆发时天体物理学家
When a star explodes, astrophysicists...
会像搜寻犯罪的线索的调查员那样
like investigators looking for clues to a crime...
深知恒星死亡后的几个小时
know that the first few hours after the stellar death...
是关键所在
are the most critical.
所以在1987年当400年里最近的超新星出现时
So in 1987, when the closest supernova...in nearly 400 years appeared...
他们知道必须快速行动
they knew they had to act fast.
它就在17万光年以外
lt was only about 170,000 light-years away...
对天文学家来说只是一箭之遥
a mere stone's throw for an astronomer.
超新星1987A在一个小星系里
Supernova1987A was in a small galaxy...
它叫大麦哲伦星云
called the Large Magellanic Cloud...
一个围绕着我们较大的银河系运转的矮星系
a dwarf galaxy that orbits around our much bigger Milky Way galaxy.
作为那年第一个超新星
Being the first supernova of that year...
这个特别的邻近的超新星
the exceptional and nearby exploding star...
简单命名为SN1987a
was simply labeled SN1987a.
然而 此时 全球数十名经验丰富的天文学家
But this time, dozens of seasoned astronomers...
做好了行动的准备
all over the planet were ready for action.
装备有尖端的工具和望远镜
Armed with sophisticated tools and telescopes...
他们将自己的注意力及装备转向天空
they turned their minds and machines to the heavens...
仔细审视超新星1987A
and closely scrutinized Supernova 1987a.
了解到超新星
Knowing that an exploding star...
在其最先几个小时里温度最高
is at its hottest in the first few hours...
并发出大量的紫外线
and is emitting lots of light in ultraviolet wavelengths...
天文学侦探们立即投入行动
the astro-detectives sprung into action.
在爆发时
At the time of the explosion...
我们看到了移动最快的东西奔我们而来
we saw the fastest-moving stuff was coming toward us...
速度达到光速的十分之一
at a tenth of the speed of light...
所以 那其实是恒星在爆发
so that was the actual star blowing up.
科学家获得了自己的爆发
Scientists had their explosion.
现在他们想知道受害者的名字
Now they wanted to know the name of the victim.
他们发现宝藏后搜遍整个已知恒星的名录
They dug through a catalog that lists all known stars...
以及它们在空中的方位
and their positions in the sky...when they struck pay dirt.
它们找到了那颗爆发的恒星
They found the star that exploded.
它就是SK-69202
lt was tagged SK-69202.
他们同时确认了那是颗大恒星
They also determined that it was a huge star...
其质量是太阳的20倍
twenty times the mass of the Sun.
检查光谱证据
Examining the spectral evidence...
科学家看到了清晰的氢线
scientists could see strong lines of hydrogen.
SN1987a具有明显的II型核塌缩超新星的特征
SN1987a bore the hallmarks...of a Type ll core-collapse supernova.
但是 为了证实自己的怀疑 证明核塌缩理论
But to confirm their suspicions and prove the core-collapse theories...
专家们必须更多一点物理证据
experts had to have one more piece of physical evidence.
他们需要中微子
They needed neutrinos...
那些科学家预言过的幽灵粒子
those ghostly particles that scientists predicted...
会在爆发时释放出来
would be unleashed during the blast.
在1980年代早期 科学家
ln the early1980s, scientists had built...
在世界各地建造了一批中微子探测器
a handful of neutrino detectors around the world.
它们装在地下深处的铁罐里
They consisted of tanks deep underground...
注满了数吨纯净水
filled with tons of pure water.
然而 这些探测器尚未捕获一个超新星中微子
But these detectors had yet to capture a single supernova neutrino.
我们这故事已经说了好长时间了
We've had this story for a long time...
就是超新星爆发 核塌缩超新星爆发的大部分能量
that most of the energy of a supernova explosion...
会变成中微子
a core-collapse supernova explosion, goes into neutrinos.
然而 我们从未看到过那些中微子
But we had never seen those neutrinos.
幸运的是
As luck would have it...
1987年2月23日他们捕捉到了自己的中微子
on February 23, 1987, they got their neutrinos.
两个探测器其中一个在日本的福冈地下
Two detectors...one beneath the city of Kamioka, Japan...
另一个在俄亥俄州伊利湖底
and the other under Lake Erie in Ohio...
捕捉到了一打难以捉摸的粒子
captured a dozen of the elusive particles.
这个容器的水里装有光探测器
There were light detectors on this volume of water...
用来观察中微子与罐子里的物质相互作用
that were used to see this little flash caused by the neutrino...
所产生的细微闪光
interacting with matter inside the tank.
有史以来 第一次地球上的科学家看到了
For the first time ever, scientists on Earth saw tangible evidence...
超新星内核产生的神秘的中微子的直接证据
of the mysterious neutrino particles...generated in the core of an exploding star.
天文学家现在知道了
Astronomers now knew...
1930年代最早提出的理论是正确的
the theories first proposed in the 1930s were right.
超新星1987A表明 毋庸置疑
Supernova1987a showed beyond a shadow of a doubt...
大质量恒星的大质量铁核
that the massive iron core of a very massive star...
塌落会形成中子星
collapsed and formed a neutron star...
因为在那个过程中
because, in that process...
会发射出大量的中微子
a lot of neutrinos should be emitted.
随着强大的太空望远镜的部署到位
With the deployment of powerful space-based telescopes...
天文学家现在已经在超新星1987A上有所发现
astronomers today have built on the astonishing discoveries...
并有所建树
made in the wake of Supernova 1987a.
2006年 三十岁的天文学家罗伯特·昆比
ln 2006, 30-year-old astronomer Robert Quimby would once again...
再次转变习惯思维
turn conventional thinking on its head...
颠覆了天文学家搜索超新星的手段
and revolutionize the way astronomers searched for supernovas.
大多数超新星搜索者
Most supernova searchers...
只想着尽可能多地发现超新星
they just want to find as many supernovas as possible...
所以 他们会每两周或每一周观察一次
so they'll look once every two weeks, every one week...
就这样你会发现它们
just so you can find them...
可以尽量观察更多的地方
and so you can look at as many fields as possible...
尽可能多找到超新星
and get as many supernovae as possible.
所以 我决定观察有限的区域
So l decided to look at a limited number offields...
尽我所能经常去观察
and look at them as of ten as l can.
雄心勃勃的宇宙侦探安排自己的机器人望远镜
The enterprising cosmic gumshoe programmed his robotic telescope...
每晚系统地扫描目标区域
to systematically sweep the targeted field every night.
就像一架星际探照灯
Like an interstellar searchlight...
锁定目标进行系统扫描
it honed in on and methodically scanned...
同一个宇宙的小小的昏暗角落
the same small, dark corner of the cosmos...
搜寻超新星疑犯
looking for supernova suspects.
他们有能快速处理数据的软件
They had sof tware that can very quickly process the data...
能告诉我是否存在以前不存在的东西
and tell me if there's anything there that wasn't there before.
一旦有这种情况 如果我认为它有可能是超新星
And when that happens, if l think it could be a supernova...
那么 我就会获取它的光谱
then l'll get a spectrum of it.
于是光谱就会告诉我那究竟是什么
And then that spectrum of it will tell me exactly what it is.
是超新星吗？是什么类型？等等
ls it a supernova? What type is it? Et cetera.
2006年9月18日 昆比有了重大的突破
On September18, 2006, Quimby got his big break.
他发现了有史以来最亮的超新星
He found the brightest supernova ever.
这是我的第四颗超新星
And this was my fourth supernova.
我不认为我该这么幸运
l didn't think that l should be so lucky.
其他人观察光谱
And others looked at the spectra...
他们开始用自己的测光手段
and they started taking their own measurements...
来测量其亮度
of the photometry, how bright it was.
他们明白了实际上2006gy
And they figured out that, in fact, 2006gy...
亮度超过了其它所有公认的超新星
was brighter than any other published supernova.
非常缓慢 它化了两个多月 70天
Very slowly, it took over two months, seventy days...
达到了最亮 然后再次衰退了
to get to the maximum light, and then faded again.
所以 它不像我们以前所见过的超新星
So it was a supernova unlike anything we'd ever seen before...
发现者是这个得克萨斯大学四年级研究生
discovered by this fourth-year graduate student...at the University of Texas.
残骸的分析表明 那颗恒星
Analysis of the remnant indicated that the star...
在爆发前其个头是太阳的100倍
before it exploded, was 100 times the size of the Sun.
由于其光谱显示有大量的氢
And with lots of hydrogen showing in its spectrum...
有记录以来最亮的超新星带有II型事件的标记
the brightest supernova ever recorded bore the stamp of a Type ll event.
于是昆比超越了自我
Then Quimby topped himself.
在他最终分析完
When he finally analyzed...
他早先发现的看似不起眼的名叫SN2005ap的超新星后
a seemingly insignificant supernova he found earlier...
他创造了了不起的发现
called SN2005ap, he made a stunning discovery.
这个东西有太阳的1000亿倍亮
lt was something like a hundred billion times...as bright as the Sun as compared to...
相对1A型超新星
For a Type 1a supernova...
最高也只有太阳的60亿倍亮
the peak may be only six billion times as bright as the Sun.
它甚至比SN2006gy还亮
lt was even brighter than SN2006gy.
就像是佐证
Like circumstantial evidence...
新的极端明亮的2005ap及其他超新星的惊人的发现
astonishing discoveries of new ultrabright supernovas...like 2005ap and others...
开创了调查超新星及其验证的全新手段
have opened up a whole new avenue of inquiry...into exploding stars and their M.O.
我们的基本想法是
The basic idea we have...
有可能这与伽玛射线爆发有着某种关联
is that perhaps this is connected somehow to gamma-ray bursts.
伽玛射线是宇宙间已知最强的光
Gamma rays are the most powerful form of light...known in the universe.
通过分析超新星
By analyzing supernovas...
调查员正比过去更接近
investigators are getting closer than ever...
解决宇宙间一些最伤脑筋的谜团
to solving some of the most confounding riddles in the cosmos.
为何其中之一产生伽玛射线
How one of them makes gamma rays...
而其它则产生普通的超新星
and the other makes an ordinary supernova...
依然是最大的谜团之一
is still one of the big mysteries.
没有谁真正知道其中的奥秘
Nobody really knows how that works.
天文学家知道的是超新星
What astronomers do know is that supernovas...
以及与之有关的伽玛射线爆发
and the gamma-ray bursts associated with them...
是宇宙间最亮的灯塔
are the brightest beacons in the universe.
在宇宙间的星系高速公路上
On the galactic highway that is the cosmos...
超新星充当着星际路标
supernovas serve as celestial signposts...
指引着天文学家前往时空的起点和终点
pointing astronomers to the beginning and the end of time and space.
航天局的史威夫特卫星于2004年发射升空
NASA's powerful Swift satellite, launched in 2004...
专门用来扫描天空
was designed specifically to sweep the sky...
侦测宇宙伽玛射线爆发
and detect gamma-ray bursts in the universe.
就像是宇宙应急第一反应员
Like cosmic first responders...
马里兰巴尔的摩的航天局戈达德宇航中心的
astrophysicists at NASA's Goddard Space Flight Center...
天体物理学家全天候值守
in Baltimore, Maryland, are standing by 24/7...
等待着史威夫特卫星的报警电话
waiting for a 911 call from Swift.
基本上在史威夫特发现伽玛射线爆发后
Basically, less than two minutes...
不到两分钟
after Swift discovered a gamma-ray burst...
卫星就会将电子邮件直接发到我们的黑莓手机上
the satellite sends down e-mails directly to our Blackberries.
不久前有颗超新星 编号SN2006aj出现时
When a recent supernova, recorded as SN2006aj, appeared...
史威夫特卫星捕捉到了它产生的骇人的伽玛射线
the Swift satellite caught the shocking gamma rays it generated.
那个伽玛射线爆发非常有趣
And that gamma-ray burst was very interesting...
因为 首先
because, first of all...
伽玛射线爆发持续的时间很长
it was a very long-duration gamma-ray burst.
通常伽玛射线爆发是一种很短暂的现象
Usually, gamma-ray bursts are very short-lived phenomena...
只有几分之一秒或几秒钟
only fractions of a second or a few seconds...
然而 这个伽玛射线爆发能够看到有35分钟
but this gamma-ray burst was visible for, like, 35 minutes.
我们看到3天后
We saw, three days later...
有个超新星在同一个位置爆发了
a supernova explosion going off at the exact same location.
这就解决了伽玛射线爆发的一个重大之谜
And this solved one of the important mysteries...
因为 我们发现至少伽玛射线爆发部分
because we found out at least parts of gamma-ray bursts...of gamma-ray bursts...
是爆发的大质量恒星引发的
are due to massive stars that are exploding.
天文学家现在看到了数百颗超新星
Astronomers today can see hundreds of supernovas...
以及它们所产生的致命的伽玛射线
and the deadly gamma-ray bursts they generate.
在宇宙高速公路上
On the cosmic highway...
科学家利用这些星际前灯
scientists use these stellar headlights...
来确定宇宙的范围与广度
to ascertain the bounds and breadth of the universe.
你可以用超新星来探测宇宙
You can use supernovae to probe the universe...
因为 如果它们很暗 你就知道它们非常遥远
'cause if they're very dim, you know they were very far away.
于是 你可以研究时空的曲度
And then you can study the curvature of space-time...
你就可以从中研究整个宇宙学
and all of the cosmology that you can study within it.
比如 如果你行进在沙漠高速公路上
For example, if you're on a desert highway...
你观察汽车的灯光
and you're looking out at the lights of the cars...
你就可以根据灯光的亮度
you can tell which are nearby and which are far away...
说出哪些在附近及哪些很遥远
from the apparent brightness of the lights.
近的看上去亮些
The ones that are nearby look bright.
而远的看上去暗些
The ones that are far away look dim.
测量物体的距离是非常系统的
Measuring how far away things are very systematically...
会告诉你宇宙的大小 年龄 形状
will tell you about the size, the age, the shape...
历史及未来
the history, the future of the universe.
事实证明1A型超新星
lt turns out that Type 1a supernovas...
最适合这个用途
are the best suited for this purpose.
关于1A型超新星的一件真正有趣的事情
One of the things that's really interesting...about the Type 1a supernovae...
那些爆发的白矮星
the ones that are exploding white dwarfs...
就是存在着固定的质量 这个詹德拉西卡质量极限
is that there is this fixed mass, this Chandrasekhar Mass...
规定了爆发的规模 涉及的物质
that sets how big the explosion is, how much stuff is involved.
其结果是 其中很多有着差不多的亮度
And the consequence of that is that many of these...have very nearly the same brightness.
如果爆发产生等量的光
lfthe explosion produces the same amount of light...
那么我们就可以测量所看到的光
then we can measure how much light we see...
来计算出超新星有多远
and figure out howfar away the supernova is.
这就是所谓的标准烛光原理
This is known as the standard candle principle.
1A型超新星就像是标准烛光
Type1a supernovae are like standard candles.
它们具有大致相同的峰值功率
They all have about the same peak power...
相同的峰值光度
the same peak luminosity.
所以 你在不同的距离观察它们
So, if you look at them from different distances...
它们就会表现出明显不同的亮度
they appear different apparent brightnesses.
如果较远则看上去就较暗
They look dimmer if they're farther away...
如果较近则看上去就较亮
and brighter if they're more nearby.
所以 如果我们在遥远星系里发现1A型超新星
So if we find Type 1a supernovae in distant galaxies...
测量其亮度
and measure their apparent brightness...
与已知的邻近的1A型超新星进行比对
and compare that with the known power...of a nearby Type 1a supernova...
我们就能够确定那颗超新星
we can determine the distance of that supernova...
以及其所在的星系的距离了
and, hence, of the galaxy in which it's located.
开创性的科技也已经让天文调查员们
The trailblazing technique has also led astro-investigators...
得出了基本的意见
to some radical conclusions.
基本上你可以利用超新星的距离
Basically, you can use the distances to supernovae...
来弄明白宇宙的行为举止以及它的年龄
to figure out what the universe is doing, how old it is.
我们现在知道根据各种证据链
And we now know that, from various lines of evidence...
它的年龄在140亿年不到一点
that it's a little less than fourteen billion years old.
但是 尤其是我们发现宇宙在加速
But, in particular, we found out the universe was accelerating...
我们曾一度认为它在其中的
when we thought it was decelerating...
引力物质的控制下在逐步减速
in the grip of the gravitational materials in it.
这就导致了一场思想革命
Thatjust caused an intellectual revolution...
就像往上扔一个球
like throwing a ball up towards the ceiling...
它不是最后回到你的手上
and rather than it having come back down into your hand...
而是越来越快地飞上去
it goes faster and faster and faster towards the ceiling.
这完全是违反直觉的
lt's completely counterintuitive.
基本上所有的天文学教科书
Basically, all the astronomy textbooks out there...
都称宇宙会减速的
all said that the universe should be decelerating...
也就是说 引力会把膨胀的速度给降下来的
that is, gravity should be slowing down the expansion rate.
然而 这个结果表明不是在慢下来
But what this result showed is that instead of slowing down...
而其实是膨胀越来越快
it was actually expanding faster and faster and faster.
虽然 超新星的调查已经帮助了科学家
While the examination of supernovas has helped scientists...
解开了许多重大的宇宙之谜
unravel many monumental cosmic mysteries...
但是 专家们认为如果他们继续追踪巨大恒星爆发
experts believe that if they continue to follow the clues...
所留下的线索
left behind when huge stars explode...
他们就有可能解答出最大的悬而未决的问题
they'll be able to answer the biggest unanswered questions.
如今 科学家们知道 不久的将来
Today, scientists know that someday soon...
我们会为自己搜索到非凡强大的超新星的
we could each witness for ourselves...
每一个证据
the marvelous and almighty force of a supernova.
我们银河系直径有10万光年
Our galaxy is 100,000 light-years across.
这就意味着 有1000个超新星发出的光
So that means there's light from a thousand supernovae...
现在正直奔我们而来
that's on its way to us now.
它均匀分布在我们的银河系里
It could even happen in ourvery own Milky Way.
在我们银河系里我们预计平均
In our galaxy, we are expected to have an average...
每百年会发生两次超新星爆发
of about two supernova explosions per century.
问题是 我们最后一次看到
The problem is that the last supernova...
我们银河系里的超新星是在近400年前
that we saw in our galaxy is almost 400 years ago...
所以 我们的银河系早已过期了
so our galaxy is long overdue.
如果它真的发生在我们的银河系
If it did happen in our own galaxy...
我们会和时空巨人
we, like the titans of space and time...
第谷 开普勒 詹德拉西卡 兹维基等人一样
Tycho, Kepler, Chandrasekhar, and Zwicky...
见证到宇宙间最具破坏性和创造性的力量:
would bearwitness to the most destructive...and the most creative force in the universe:
超新星
The supernova.
谢谢观赏
Thanks For Viewing